A Guide to the Daniel J. Kevles papers FA497
Rockefeller Archive Center
Daniel J. Kevles papers
1955-2000
Rockefeller Archive Center
Kevles, Daniel J.
FA497
12.73 Cubic Feet 34 document boxes: 33 letter box and 1 half-letter letter box
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the research files science historian Daniel J. Kevles created in the preparation and writing of a few of his books.
There are two series in the collection. Each series pertains to a different one of Kevles' books. The first series contains oral history interview transcripts for the book In the Name of Eugenics: Genetics and the Uses of Human Heredity (1985). The second series contains various types of materials documenting Kevles' researching the affair surrounding the allegations of scientific misconduct against Thereza Imanishi-Kari and his preparing his book The David Baltimore Case: A Trial of Politics, Science, and Character (1998).
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement
The collection consists of 2 series with the second series further subdivided into 4 subseries.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Human Genetics Interviews, 1982-1984
Series 2. David Baltimore Case Research Files
Subseries 2.1. Photographs, 1977-1997
Subseries 2.2. Case research and book preparation, 1955-2000
Subseries 2.3. Hearings transcripts, 1988-1995
Subseries 2.4. New Yorker article, 1988-1996
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to the RAC in several different accessions between 2003 and 2015. These accessions were ingested as Accessions 2003:054, 2011:053, and 2015:108.
Human genetics; Eugenics -- History; Ethics; HIV (Viruses); Immunology; Medical sciences; Pathology
- Human Genetics Interviews, 1982-1984; 1; 0.57 Cubic Feet 2 document boxes: 1 letter box and 1 half-letter box
  Arrangement
  Files in the series are arranged alphabetically by last name of the interviewee.
  Scope and Contents
  Daniel J. Kevles, a historian of science, then at the California Institute of Technology, conducted a series of interviews in the early 1980s as research for his book, In the Name of Eugenics: Genetics and the Uses of Human Heredity, first published in 1985. As part of his project, he interviewed 39 medical, human, and molecular geneticists from the United States and the United Kingdom. He selected these scientists based on their involvement from the 1930s to 1950s with the process to establish human and medical genetics on an epistemologically-sound footing, devoid of the class and race biases and the methodological flaws that infused the study of human heredity during the heyday of the eugenics movement. Kevles' interviewees included Alexander Bearn, Walter Bodmer, Barton Childs, Harry Harris, Patricia Jacobs, Joshua Lederberg, Jerome Lejeune, Victor McKusick, James V. Neel, Paul E. Polani, Laurence Snyder, and Arthur Steinberg.
  - Walter Bodmer, 1982 July 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Biographical / Historical
    Interview: Imperial Cancer Research Institute, London, England
  - Peggy Brewer-Musgrave and Richard Musgrave, 1984 April 27 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Interview: San Francisco, CA
  - John Burn, 1984 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Interview: The Institute for Child Health, London, England
  - Cedric Carter, 1982 June 21 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Interview: Clinical Genetics Unit, Institute for Child Health, London, England
  - Luigi Luca Cavalli-Sforza, 1984 April 13 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Interview: By telephone - from Pasadena, CA to Palo Alto, CA
  - Barton Childs, 1982 April 9 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Interview: Johns Hopkins University Hospital
  - Cyril Clark, 1982 July 5 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Interview: London, England
  - Bernard Davis, 1984 March 16 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Interview: Harvard Medical School
  - John Edwards, 1984 March 23 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Interview: Department of Biochemistry, Oxford University
  - Charles J. Epstein, 1984 April 27 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Interview: University of San Francisco Medical School, San Francisco, CA
  - Charles Ford, 1982 June 25 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Interview: Oxford, England (Vicinity)
  - Park Gerald, 1982 June 8 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Interview: Boston's Children's Hospital, Boston, MA
  - Harry Harris, 1982 November 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Interview: University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA
  - Kurt Hirschorn, 1984 March 13 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Interview: Mt. Sinai Medical School, New York City
  - Pat Jacobs, 1983 October 6 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Interview: By telephone - from Cal Tech to University of Hawaii
  - Hans Kalmus, 1982 July 2 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Interview: The Galton Laboratory, University College London, London, England
  - Sylvia Lawler, 1982 June 29 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Conditions Governing Access
    The RAC allows use of this material in accordance with the relevant sections of US copyright law that facilitate fair use. The RAC explicitly does not own copyright for the content of the interviews and, as such, cannot grant permission to publish any component of this material. The responsibility remains with the researcher to obtain permission from the holders of these rights.
  - Joshua Lederberg, 1984 March 13 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Interview: Rockefeller University, New York City
  - Jerome Lejeune, 1982 July 8 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Interview: Paris, France
  - O. J. Miller, 1984 March 12 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Interview: Columbia College of Physicians and Surgeons
  - Aubrey Milunsky, 1984 March 16 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Interview: Boston University School of Medicine
  - Ursula Mittwoch, 1982 June 28 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - James V. Neel, 1982 May 26 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Interview: Ann Arbor, MI
  - Paul Polani, 1982 June 22 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Interview: Pediatric Research Unit, Guy's Hospital Medical School, London, England
  - Paul Polani, 1984 March 22 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - James Renwick, 1984 March 22 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Interview: London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine
  - J. A. Fraser Roberts, 1982 June 29 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Interview: Royal Society of London
  - Leon Rosenberg, 1984 March 14 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Interview: Yale University Medical School, New Haven, CT
  - Francis H. Ruddle, 1984 March 15 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Yale University Medical School. Interview at Parker House, Boston, MA
  - Arthur Salisbury, 1982 May 18 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Interview: New York City
  - Ruth Sanger, 1982 June 23 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Interview: Medical Research Council, Blood Group Unit, University College London, London, England
  - Harry Shapiro, 1984 March 12 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Interview: American Museum of Natural History, New York City
  - Cedric A. B. Smith, 1982 July 2 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - John Maynard Smith, 1983 June 28 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Interview: Kingston, East Sussex, England
  - Laurence Snyder, 1983 April 29 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Interview: By telephone - from Pasadena, CA to Hawaii
  - Arthur Steinberg, 1982 May 28 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Interview: Case Western Reserve Medical School, Cleveland, OH
- David Baltimore Case Research Files, 1955-2000; 2; 12.16 Cubic Feet 32 document boxes: 32 letter boxes
  The series consists of 4 subseries.
  Most of the hearing transcripts in Subseries 2.3 have been arranged chronologically.
  Series arrangement is as follows:
  Subseries 2.1. Photographs, 1977-1997
  Subseries 2.2. Case research and book preparation, 1955-2000
  Subseries 2.3. Hearings transcripts, 1988-1995
  Subseries 2.4. New Yorker article, 1988-1996
  This series contains materials related to Daniel J. Kevles' research and preparation for his book The David Baltimore Case: A Trial of Politics, Science, and Character about the investigations into allegations of scientific misconduct against Thereza Imanishi-Kari, David Baltimore's role in the case, and the events surrounding it.
  The allegations of misconduct regarded data Imanishi-Kari put into an article for the Science Journal, Cell which Baltimore coauthored ("Altered Repertoire of Endogenous Immunoglobulin Gene Expression in Transgenic Mice Containing a Rearranged Mu Heavy Chain Gene", published in 1986). The allegations originated from concerns raised by a postdoctoral fellow in Imanishi-Kari's laboratory at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Margot O'Toole. Investigations and hearings regarding the concerns and the later allegations of misconduct and fraud spanned across several years and were conducted by a number of different organizations, including MIT, the National Institutes of Health (NIH), the United States House of Representatives Committee on Energy and Commerce Subcommittee on Oversight and Investigations, the Office of Scientific Integrity (OSI), OSI's successor, the Office of Research Integrity (ORI), and the Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) Department Appeals Board (DAB). The conclusion of the case came in 1996 when DAB decided that ORI did not prove its case that Imanishi-Kari committed fraud.
  Baltimore is associated with the case because of his refusal to retract the paper and defense of Imanishi-Kari and because of his status and leadership in the scientific community as a Nobel Laureate. A lot of the media coverage and commentary within the scientific community centered him. Also, some of the investigations probed his response to O'Toole's concerns. Because of the controversy, Baltimore resigned from the presidency of Rockefeller University.
  Users will see how the file names and documents within the series use terms like the "Imanishi-Kari case" and the "Baltimore case" interchangeably. They all reference these events.
  The series is comprised of four subseries. The first subseries contains photographs related to images Kevles used in his book, and it documents his acquiring and deciding the images to incorporate. Materials documenting Kevles researching, drafting, and promoting the book comprise the second subseries. Subseries 2.3 contains transcripts of various hearings regarding the Imanishi-Kari case. Lastly, the fourth subseries has documents pertaining to an article Kevles wrote for the New Yorker about the case ahead of the publication of his book.
  In addition to providing insight into the proceedings of the Imanishi-Kari case, the series also documents discussions, controversy, and ideologies about the nature of scientific research fraud and misconduct, the prevalence of it, how it should be responded to and investigated, and the nature of scientific research integrity and ethics.
  - Photographs, 1977-1997; 1; .285 Cubic Feet .75 document box: .75 letter box
    This subseries documents Daniel J. Kelves obtaining and organizing photographs to use in his book The David Baltimore Case: A Trial of Politics, Science, and Character. The photographs are mostly of the principal individuals involved in the investigation into the allegations of data fabrication against David Baltimore's co-author Thereza Imanishi-Kari.
    The subseries is comprised of two files. The first file contains materials that document Kevles requesting, acquiring, and deciding the photographs he used for the book. There are photo use requests, invoices, correspondence, drafts, and book page mockups. The images in the file include photographs and photograph negatives. Other materials in the file include articles, newsletters, and reports.
    The photographs in the second file were organized into a binder. Information attached to the images explain where in the book Kevles intended to insert specific photos. There are also descriptions of who or what is depicted in the photographs and credit information about where the photographs originated.
    The subjects of the photographs in the subseries include:
    Judith Ballard, David Baltimore, Bruce Chafin, Joseph Davie, Bernard Davis, John D. Dingell, John Edsal, Herman Eisen, Ned Feder, Walter Gilbert, Suzanne Hadley, Jules Hallum, Bernadine Healy, Alice Huang, Briggite Huber, Hugh McDevitt, Joan Press, Mark Ptashne, Bruce Singal, Cecilia Sparks Ford, Walter Stewart, Ursula Storb, Peter Stockton, Tom Watson, Robert Woodland, Henry Wortis, and Julius Youngner.
    - Images for book, 1977-1997; File contains still images, including photographs and photograph negatives. (Box 3, Folder 37-41)
    - David Baltimore case photographs (originals), 1989-1997; File contains still images, including photographs. (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Case research and book preparation, 1955-2000; 2; 7.885 Cubic Feet 20.75 document boxes: 20.75 letter boxes
    This subseries contains the materials Daniel Kevles acquired and created through his research of the affair surrounding allegations of scientific misconduct against Thereza Imanishi-Kari and his writing of his book The David Baltimore Case: A Trial of Politics, Science, and Character.
    There are several major components of the subseries. They include:
    - Discovery materials prepared by Imanishi-Kari's legal team for her appeal to the United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) Department Appeals Board (DAB)
    - Documents pertaining to the Imanishi-Kari case Kevles obtained under the Freedom of Information Act (FOIA)
    - Proceedings of the different investigations and hearings pertaining to the Cell paper and the Imanishi-Kari case; there are interview transcripts, reports, briefs, findings, and decisions; these investigations and hearings include the National Institutes of Health (NIH) Panel, John D. Dingell's Subcommittee on Oversight and Investigations of the House of Representatives Committee on Energy and Commerce, the Office of Scientific Integrity (OSI), the Office of Research Integrity (ORI), and the HHS DAB
    - Interviews conducted by Kevles with individuals involved in the Imanishi-Kari case; there are interview transcripts, notes on interviews, questions for interviews, correspondence and other documents showing Kevles trying to contact individuals, and trip files for visits Kevles made to conduct interviews
    - Materials concerning the broader issues around scientific research misconduct, fraud, integrity, ethics, and oversight; these materials largely concern other examples of scientific misconduct investigations like the Robert Gallo HIV discovery case, the efforts of NIH staff members Walter Stewart and Ned Feder to investigate scientific fraud outside of the allegations in the Imanishi-Kari case, procedures and policies for responding to allegations of scientific misconduct, and questions regarding what are scientific research ethics, how serious are issues of scientific misconduct, are instances of scientific misconduct being adequately responded to, and how should scientific misconduct be investigated and handled
    - Materials about the impact of the Imanishi-Kari case on David Baltimore; these materials concern Baltimore stepping down from his presidency at Rockefeller University and both support and criticism of Baltimore and his actions within the scientific community
    - Media coverage of the Imanishi-Kari case; there are articles and newspaper clippings
    - Materials documenting Kevles preparing his book for publication
    - Materials documenting Kevles promote his book; this includes media coverage of the book and talks and lectures Kevles gave about the book and the Imanishi-Kari case
    - Los Angeles Times Magazine article and Sondra Schlesinger interviews, 1995-1997 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - The science of immunology, 1986-1994 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Miscellaneous materials incorporated in proofs, 1987-1998 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Joseph Onek - Interviews and other documents, 1993-1996 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Joseph Onek discovery index for Thereza Imanishi-Kari case, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Joseph Onek discovery files - Walter Stewart and Ned Feder, 1986-1989 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Joseph Onek discover files, 1986-1990 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Joseph Onek discovery files post-1991, 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Joseph Onek discovery files - Office of Scientific Integrity (OSI), 1990-1993 (Box 4, Folder 51-52)
    - National Institute of Health (NIH) investigation, 1987-1997 (Box 5, Folder 53-54)
    - National Institute of Health (NIH) January 1989 report on investigation, 1986-1995 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Thereza Imanishi-Kari appeal exhibits, 1995-1997 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Thereza Imanishi-Kari appeal documents, 1984-1989 (Box 5, Folder 57-58)
    - Thereza Imanishi-Kari appeals exhibits, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 59-60)
    - Jules Hallum, 1993-1996 (Box 6, Folder 61)
    - Margot O'Toole research, 1962-1996 (Box 6, Folder 62)
    - Walter Stewart and Ned Feder, 1965-1996 (Box 6, Folder 63-65)
    - Walter Stewart and Ned Feder, 1986-1992 (Box 6, Folder 66-67)
    - Walter Stewart and Ned Feder post-1993, 1993-1996 (Box 7, Folder 68)
    - Al Gore 1981 biomedical research fraud hearings, 1981-1997 (Box 7, Folder 69)
    - Scientific Fraud and Misconduct in American Political Culture article - Draft and research, 1980-1996 (Box 7, Folder 70)
    - Betrayers of the Truth, 1981-1996 (Box 7, Folder 71)
    - Jock Friedly, 1991-1997 (Box 7, Folder 72)
    - John D. Dingell - United States House of Representatives Committee on Energy and Commerce, 1990-1997 (Box 7, Folder 73)
    - Court cases with United States government agencies, 1966-1979 (Box 7, Folder 74)
    - Hearing before the United States House of Representatives Committee on Science and Technology, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 75)
    - Hearing before the United States House of Representatives Committee on the Judiciary - Libel, 1986-1996 (Box 8, Folder 76)
    - Ted Weiss hearing on Scientific Fraud and Misconduct and the Federal Response, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 77)
    - John D. Dingell documents, 1988-1990 (Box 8, Folder 78)
    - John D. Dingell August 1991 hearing on Scientific Fraud, 1991-1992 (Box 8, Folder 79)
    - Bernadine Healy - Office of Scientific Integrity (OSI) and John D. Dingell, 1976-1996 (Box 8, Folder 80)
    - Banbury Center January 1989 conference - The Ethos of Scientific Research, 1988-1995 (Box 8, Folder 81)
    - Donald Kennedy - Stanford University Indirect Costs Controversy, 1992-1996 (Box 8, Folder 82)
    - Documents obtained under the Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) - Thereza Imanishi-Kari case, 1986-1997 (Box 8, Folder 83)
    - Documents obtained under the Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) - Thereza Imanishi-Kari case, 1988-1997 (Box 8, Folder 84)
    - Office of Research Integrity (ORI) documents index, 1995-1997 (Box 9, Folder 85)
    - Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) requests - Office of Research Integrity (ORI) investigation, 1995-1997 (Box 9, Folder 86)
    - National Institutes of Health (NIH) 1988 panel (Box 9, Folder 87)
    - Ursula Storb, Joseph Davie, and Hugh McDevitt interviews, 1996-1997 (Box 9, Folder 88)
    - National Institutes of Health (NIH) Panel May 3, 1989 meeting with Cell article authors, 1989-1992 (Box 9, Folder 89-90)
    - Christopher Albanese February 2, 1990 interview with Office of Scientific Integrity (OSI) (Box 10, Folder 91-92)
    - David Baltimore April 30, 1990 interview with Office of Scientific Integrity (OSI) (Box 10, Folder 93)
    - Thereza Imanishi-Kari October 13, 1990 interview with Office of Scientific Integrity (OSI) (Box 10, Folder 94)
    - Thereza Imanishi-Kari May 10, 1990 press conference (Box 10, Folder 95)
    - Margot O'Toole May 17, 1988 interview with National Institutes of Health (NIH) (Box 10, Folder 96)
    - Margot O'Toole 1990 interviews with Office of Scientific Integrity (OSI), 1990-1992 (Box 10, Folder 97)
    - Moema Reis 1990 interviews with Office of Scientific Integrity (OSI) (Box 10, Folder 98)
    - Charles Maplethorpe February 11, 1990 interview with Office of Scientific Integrity (OSI), 1985-1991 (Box 11, Folder 99-100)
    - Charles Maplethorpe December 27, 1989 interview with Office of Scientific Integrity (OSI), 1989-1990 (Box 11, Folder 101)
    - Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) interviews with Office of Scientific Integrity (OSI), 1991 (Box 11, Folder 102)
    - David Weaver June 14, 1990 interview with Office of Scientific Integrity (OSI), 1990-1991 (Box 11, Folder 103)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - David Baltimore, January 23, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 104)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - David Baltimore and Alice Huang, June 16, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 105)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - David Baltimore, March 20, 1996, 1993-1996 (Box 11, Folder 106)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Paul Berg, April 8, 1996 (Box 11, Folder 107)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Melvin Bosma, June 22, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 108)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Joseph Davie, October 28, 1996 (Box 12, Folder 109)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Paul Doty, June 3, 1997, 1992-1997 (Box 12, Folder 110)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - John Edsall, October 1, 1992, 1955-1997 (Box 12, Folder 111)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Herman Eisen, 1992, 1986-1993 (Box 12, Folder 112)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Martin Flax, October 7, 1992 (Box 12, Folder 113)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Maurice Fox, October 2, 1992 (Box 12, Folder 114)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Walter Gilbert, October 2, 1992, 1991-1992 (Box 12, Folder 115)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Suzanne Hadley, 1991-1996 (Box 12, Folder 116)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Rollin Hotchkiss and Magda Gabor, 1996-1997 (Box 12, Folder 117)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Bernadine Healy, 1996-1997 (Box 12, Folder 118)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Leonore and Leonard Herzenberg, July 2, 1996 (Box 12, Folder 119)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Brigitte Huber, October 1992, 1992-1996 (Box 12, Folder 120)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Vivian Ingras, December 11, 1992, 1992-1993 (Box 12, Folder 121)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Thereza Imanishi-Kari, March 20, 1996 (Box 12, Folder 122)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Thereza Imanishi-Kari, March 20, 1996, 1990-1996 (Box 12, Folder 123)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Thereza Imanishi-Kari, October 28, 1996 (Box 12, Folder 124)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Thereza Imanishi-Kari, October 6, 1992, 1970-1997 (Box 12, Folder 125)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Brian Kimes, March 25, 1996 (Box 12, Folder 126)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Robert Lanman, June 6, 1996 (Box 12, Folder 127)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Mary Miers, March 24, 1993, 1993-1996 (Box 12, Folder 128)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Bruce Maurer, November 1, 1996, 1996-1997 (Box 12, Folder 129)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Joan Press, June 18, 1996 (Box 12, Folder 130)
      Restricted confidential material Open in 2038
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Mark Ptashne, May 28, 1997 (Box 13, Folder 131)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Charles Maplethorpe, March 23, 1993, 1993-1996 (Box 13, Folder 132)
    - Information regarding Charles Maplethorpe, 1985-1996 (Box 13, Folder 133)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Matt Meselsohn, October 27, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 134)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Margot O'Toole, 1992, 1992-1997 (Box 13, Folder 135-136)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Chris Pascal, May 1996 (Box 13, Folder 137)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Joseph Rall, March 25, 1996 (Box 13, Folder 138)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Walter Stewart and Ned Feder, September 16, 1992, 1992-1995 (Box 13, Folder 139)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Peter Stockton and Bruce Chafin, March 14, 1993, 1993-1995 (Box 13, Folder 140)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Ursula Storb, April 8, 1997 (Box 13, Folder 141)
    - Terence Speed, 1997 (Box 13, Folder 142)
    - David Baltimore, California Institute of Technology President/Walter Stewart and Ned Feder clippings, 1988-1997 (Box 13, Folder 143)
      Restricted Executive Search Open in 2038